A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Administration, Building Services, Ford Foundation Headquarters, New Building Planning and Construction Files FA500
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Administration, Building Services, Ford Foundation Headquarters, New Building Planning and Construction Files
1951-2011 (Bulk: 1963-1969)
1963-1969
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA500
28 Cubic Feet
The New Building Planning and Construction Files span from 1951 to 1998, with the bulk of the files documenting the construction and initial occupation of the building (1964-1969). The files originate from the Foundation's Administrative Division and touch upon all aspects of the design and construction process. The earliest documents in the collection concern the acquisition of the property at 320 E. 43rd Street, site demolition, and the architectural design. The files document all aspects of the construction of the building, as well as building operations. Other files hold publicity about the new headquarters. The collection also contains photographs and slides of the site demolition and construction, the garden and offices in the completed building, and several individuals including architect Kevin Roche, who achieved recognition for his creative work with glass.
(66 boxes. 61 letter-size document boxes, 1 legal-size document box, 4 oversize boxes.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials
Appendix A: Reports – Unpublished reports written by Ford Foundation staff and consultants were removed from their original folders, scanned and transferred to the Archives' collection of staff and consultant reports. See Appendix A for a list of these reports and their specific assigned number. The reports are listed in alphabetical order by author. The assigned number may be used to access reports in the online catalog.
Sixty-five photographs are listed on the inventory as separated and framed for display. Of these, 30 have been visually recorded, wrapped and prepared for offsite storage.
Foundation Headquarters History
Before 1953 the Ford Foundation occupied executive offices in Pasadena, California and general offices at various locations throughout New York City. In the autumn of 1952, Treasurer Oliver May signed a lease for space in 477 Madison Avenue to unite the Foundation's New York operations within a single building and, early in the following year, a decision was made to relocate the executive offices to New York City. The combined Pasadena and New York staff consolidated into one office at 477 Madison Avenue in June 1954.
The Foundation continued to expand and, between 1958 and 1961, the Board of Trustees considered the possibility of moving to a larger building or transferring some of its staff to a separate building. In early 1963, the Board decided to construct a new building for the entire Foundation and engaged a realtor to locate the site. The site chosen was that of the former Grand Central Hospital at 321 East 42nd Street, originally built in 1912 for the Hospital for the Ruptured and Crippled (now the Hospital for Special Surgery). The Foundation appointed a Trustees' Building Committee on March 28-29, 1963, purchased the hospital grounds on April 1st, and took possession of the property on June 13th. A planning committee of six, responsible for the preparation of construction requirements and the selection of an architect, was formed shortly thereafter. The Ford Foundation selected the architectural firm Eero Saarinen and Associates (later known as Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates) to design the building. In July 1963, the Foundation purchased additional property to enable the lot to encompass a full rectangle. Turner Construction Company became the general contractor on July 30, 1963 and the Foundation signed a demolition contract with the Lipsett Division of Luria Brothers on August 6. The Luria Brothers completed the demolition of the hospital and a three-story apartment building in the northeast corner of the property in February 1964.
Preliminary site excavation began on May 1, 1964. In the same month, the Trustees' Building Committee approved the initial design for a 246,000 square foot building, exclusive of garden and terraces, with executive offices on the 11th floor and restaurant facilities on the 12th floor. In December, the Committee authorized the use of Cor-Ten weathering steel in lieu of reinforced concrete. The neighboring Hermitage apartment building threatened the Foundation with a lawsuit in November 1964 over the loss of access to light and air that would result from the new construction. The litigious parties settled out of court several months later.
Construction began in March 1965 with an initial budget of $22 million, and was completed less than two years later, but somewhat over budget. By June 1967 the estimated costs had risen to $25.5 million. The building was dedicated on December 8, 1967, although some floors had been occupied since September. In 1995, the American Institute of Architects and the American Architectural Foundation presented the Ford Foundation Headquarters Building with a Twenty Five Year Award given to buildings and structures that have "stood the test of time for 25 to 35 years" and that "[exemplify] design of enduring significance." Two years later, on October 21, 1997, the New York City Landmarks Preservation Commission awarded the building Landmark status.
Kevin Roche, the primary architect of the building, was recruited in 1950 by Eero Saarinen and Associates. By 1954, he had become the Principal Design Associate to Mr. Saarinen and assisted him on all projects until Mr. Saarinen's death in September 1961. In 1963 the Ford Foundation hired Eero Saarinen and Associates to design the new headquarters building at 320 E. 43nd Street. In 1966 Roche and his colleague, John Dinkeloo, changed the name of Eero Saarinen and Associates to Kevin Roche John Dinkeloo and Associates.
Organizational History
The Division of Administration oversaw the construction of the headquarters building and was tasked with building maintenance after construction. The Foundation formally established a Division of Administration in 1964 with responsibilities that grew to encompass the offices of the Vice President, Comptroller, and Personnel (added in 1966), Building Services (1967), Logistical Services (1968), and Program Related Investments (1969). In 1980, the Division of Organization and Management replaced the Division of Administration.
The Building Services Department was responsible for supervising the work of the contractors who provided food, operated and maintained the building; purchased, stored and distributed office supplies and equipment; printed and photocopied staff documents; purchased furniture and furnishings for the building; provided reception, telephone, and conference services; and ensured the building met fire, safety, and sanitation standards. Building services also maintained many of the construction records.
Biographical History
On December 10, 1964, Dr. Verne S. Atwater was asked by Ford Foundation President Henry T. Heald to assume overall responsibility for the planning and construction of the new building.
He earned a B.A. in 1942 from Heidelberg College, an MBA from Harvard Business School, and a PhD from New York University's School of Business in 1961, which he completed while attending classes at night. Following his graduation, Dr. Atwater served for two years as the Ford Foundation's first Representative in Latin America before being promoted to administrative Vice President and Director of the Latin America Program. By January 1965 he had reassigned his Latin American responsibilities to others in order to focus on administration. He resigned from the Foundation in May 1968 to become Chairman and CEO of the Central Savings Bank in New York. He later joined the faculty of Pace University, where he taught finance from 1982 to his retirement in 2002.
Rollin H. "R.H." McCarthy was the Director of Building Planning and Construction. He also worked with members of both the Foundation's management and the Trustees' Building Committee. He served as Director and ex officio on the Trustees' Building Committee from 1963 until he resigned in February 1, 1966 for health reasons.
Ralph G. Schwarz was the Director of Administrative Services. He replaced Mr. McCarthy as Director of Building Planning and Construction on February 1, 1966 and became an ex officio member of the Trustees' Building Committee.
Scope and Content Note
The New Building Planning and Construction Files span from 1951 to 2011. The bulk of the files, dating from 1964 to 1969, document the construction and initial occupation of the building. The collection originates from the Foundation's Administrative Division and describes all aspects of the design and construction process. The earliest documents in the collection, 1963-1964, pertain to the acquisition of the property at 320 E. 43rd Street, the site demolition, and the design process. The majority of the files relates to physical construction, while others describe building operations or contain publicity for the new headquarters. The collection also contains photographs and slides of the demolition of the hospital, the construction, the completed 12-story atrium, lush garden and offices, and the architect, Kevin Roche.
Related Collections
FA622 Ford Foundation records, Office files of Henry T. Heald, 1951, 1956-1966, 1956-1966 (bulk). Mr. Heald's Trustee Building Committee files contain information about the construction of the Foundation's Headquarters on East 43rd Street, New York City.
The "as built" plans are maintained and held on-site by the Facilities Management Department. The plans are divided by area: structural, electrical, plumbing, et cetera.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
- Publicity and Awards, Bulk, 1962-1997 1962-2011 (bulk 1962-1997); 1962-1997; I (Box not specified)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. Publicity and Awards, 1962-2011
  This series comprises articles, magazines, press releases, and other documentation about the architecture and construction of the Ford Foundation's Headquarters Building. The files are arranged chronologically and include fact sheets created about the building, the dedication brochure (1967), pamphlets produced by the Foundation about the building and the garden (1971) and correspondence between members of the Building Planning Committee concerning public relations planning (1963-1964) and the media response (1966-1968). The series also includes files for the Twenty Five Year Award received from the American Institute of Architects and the American Architectural Foundation in 1995 and the granting of Landmark status in 1997. Included in the files of "media response" is a 1968 issue of Architectural Record that recognized the building as 'a new kind of urban space' and the March 29, 1968 issue of Life magazine with a feature article on the new building.
  - Ford Foundation Building Facts -- Photographs (separated) -- Fact Sheets and News Articles, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Building Planning Committee -- Publicity and Preview, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ford Foundation Building Facts and Press Clippings -- Fact Sheets, Press Releases, Miscellaneous News Clippings, 1963-1982 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - New Building -- Publicity -- General -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, Public Relations Releases and Clippings, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Excerpts -- Clippings Re: Ford Foundation, Contractors, Architectural Styles, 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - "New York Headquarters Enclosing A Garden," Architectural Record, November 1964, Nov 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Magnum Photographs -- New Building -- Film -- Memoranda, Invoice and Contract Re: 16mm Film of Building, Jun 21, 1966-Oct 10, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building the Ford Foundation -- Building Committee -- Dr. Stratton's File, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Public Relations -- Memoranda and Proposal Re: New Building Public Relations, Mar-Aug 1967 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Ford Flies High," New York Times, Nov 26, 1967 (reprint) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Press Coverage -- News Clippings File, Nov-Dec 1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ford Foundation Building Dedication Ceremonies -- Brochure, Dec 8, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building the Ford Foundation -- Dedication of Building -- Invitation, Pamphlets, Brochures, Dec 8, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - New Building Dedication -- General Information, Dec 1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Publicity -- Magazines and Fact Sheet, Dec 1967-Jan 1968 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building the Ford Foundation -- Art Purchases/Selections, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Charity Begins At Home," Progressive Architecture, February 1968, Feb 1968 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "The Ford Foundation Building," Architectural Record, Feb 1968 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "New York's Indoor Forest," American Forests, March 1968, Mar 1968 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - "A Grant to Beauty," Life, 3/29/1968 (full issue), Mar 39, 1968 (Box 63, Folder 1)
  - "Donacion Al Arte," Life en Espanol, 4/22/1968 (full issue), Apr 22, 1968 (Box 63, Folder 2)
  - "The Granite, Glass and Garden Community," Fortune, Apr 1968 (full issue) (Box 63, Folder 3)
  - "Verwaltungsgebaude der Ford Foundation," Moebel Interior Design, May 1968 (full issue) (Box 62, Folder 1)
  - "A House of New York League Values," Architectural Design, July 1968 (full issue), Jul 1968 (Box 62, Folder 2)
  - "The Ford Foundation Building," Audience, Spring 1968 (full issue) (Box 62, Folder 3)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building the Ford Foundation -- Articles from Architectural Record, Kevin Roche Statement, Other Clippings, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Ford Building Still Drawing Visitors," New York Times, August 30, 1970, Aug 30, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Ford and La Raza," Ramparts, September 1970, Sep 1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - The Garden of the Ford Foundation -- Brochure by Ford Foundation, Apr 24, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - The Ford Foundation Building -- Brochure by Ford Foundation, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Building Photograph Requests -- Cover Letters, 1972-1982 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Art of the Ford Foundation Building -- Brochure by Ford Foundation, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "Henry Ford II," New York Times Magazine, 3/5/1978 (full issue), Mar 5, 1978 (Box 63, Folder 4)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building of the Ford Foundation -- Ford Foundation Headquarters Building 25 Year Award -- American Institute of Architects/American Architectural Foundation, Jan 1995 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Office of the Secretary -- Building the Ford Foundation -- New York City Landmark Preservation, Sep 16, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Ford Foundation "75 Years of Change" Celebration -- Pamphlet and Kevin Roche City Museum of New York Exhibit Booklet, Oct 27, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Design and Planning, Bulk, 1963-1968 1951-1970 (bulk 1963-1968); 1963-1968; II (Box not specified)
  Series II. Design and Planning, 1951-1970 (bulk 1963-1967)
  This series, arranged alphabetically by subject, details the process of designing and planning the Ford Foundation's new headquarters building. The files include drawings, specifications, and proposals for structural components. They also document site acquisition, demolition of the existing hospital structure, and relations with the Tudor City Community. One document of note is a letter dated August 25, 1966 and signed by architect Kevin Roche and his partner John Dinkeloo, announcing the change in the architectural design firm's name from Eero Saarinen and Associates to Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo and Associates. The letter is located in the "Architects-Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo & Associates (1965-1966)" file.
  - 326 East 43rd Street -- Berk Industries Property Acquisition -- Correspondence Re: Hospital Cornerstone Property, Jun 7, 1963-Mar 9, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 477 Madison Avenue -- Floor Plans, Miscellaneous -- Old Building, Sep 24, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - 800 Second Avenue -- Correspondence Re: Air Duct, Jul 8-Dec 12, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Architects -- Addendum, Jun 21-Jul 23, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Architects -- Building Specifications (1 of 2), May 3, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Architects -- Building Specifications (2 of 2), May 3, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Architects -- Bulletins, Jan 19, 1965-Jan 28, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Architects -- Deere & Co. (Eero Saarinen) Information Booklet, Jun 5, 1964 (Box 62, Folder 4)
  - Architects -- Eero Saarinen and Associates -- Cost Estimate, Jun 11, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Architects -- Eero Saarinen and Associates -- Model Furniture Mock-Ups, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Architects -- Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo and Associates (Eero Saarinen and Associates) -- Correspondence inc. Signed Letter by Roche and Dinkeloo (1 of 3), 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Architects -- Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo and Associates (Eero Saarinen and Associates) -- Correspondence (2 of 3), 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Architects -- Kevin Roche, John Dinkeloo and Associates (Eero Saarinen and Associates) -- Correspondence (3 of 3), 1965-1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Architects -- Selection -- Correspondence, 1954-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Architects -- Selection -- Correspondence and background, Sep 1962-Feb 1964 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Architects -- "SKA" Sketches and Drawings -- Building Specifications, Mock-Up Rooms, Revision Plans (1 of 2), Dec 1967-Jan 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Architects -- "SKA" Sketches and Drawings (2 of 2), Dec 1967-Jan 1968 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Architects -- "SKA" Sketches and Drawings -- Reception Desk (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Architects -- Specifications for Furniture -- Eero Saarinen and Associates, Apr 14, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Area Computations, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Area Studies and Occupancy Plans, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Building Design -- Correspondence Re: Planning, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Building Design -- Memoranda, Reports, Specifications, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Building Drawings -- Microfiche, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Building Planning Committee -- Minutes Re: Planning, Design, Construction, Jun 6, 1963-Dec 21, 1964 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Building Planning Committee -- Minutes, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ceilings -- Correspondence Re: Acoustic Tile Bids, Jan 4, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Cellar Plan -- Memoranda, Mar 14-Mar 24, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Complaints -- From Tudor City Re: New Building, Sep 30, 1964-Jan 25, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Contract File -- Inventory List, Contract File, Tax Documents, 1951-1964 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cor-Ten Steel -- Proposal (inc. photographs), [1963] (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Cor-Ten Steel -- Memoranda, Proposal and Background (see: Visual Images - Slides), 1967-1968 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Data Processing -- Memoranda Re: Computer Room, May 21-Jun 16, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Demolition of Existing Structure -- Correspondence, Demolition Agreement, Insurance, Area Plans, etc. (1 of 2), Mar 14, 1963-Aug 8, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Demolition of Existing Structure -- Correspondence Re: Progress, Demolition Plan, Insurance Certificates, etc. (2 of 2), Aug 6, 1963-Apr 6, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Department of Water, Gas and Electricity -- Correspondence and Area Map Re: Street Lighting Relocation, Apr 5-Jul 12, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Design Analyses and Computations (1 of 3), Jan-Mar 1965 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Design Analyses and Computations (2 of 3), Jan-Mar 1965 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Design Analyses and Computations (3 of 3), Jan-Mar 1965 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Design Committee -- Meeting Minutes (1 of 3), May 18, 1964-Aug 18, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Design Committee -- Meeting Minutes (2 of 3), Aug 31, 1964-Aug 24, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Design Committee -- Meeting Minutes (3 of 3), Aug 11, 1965-Jan 18, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Design Referral Memoranda (1 of 2), Nov 8, 1965-Mar 21, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Design Referral Memoranda (2 of 2), 1965-1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Designs and Specifications -- Memoranda, Specifications, Analysis, 1964-1965 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Dining Room -- Sketch Drawing, Jun 5, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Display Museum -- Brief Memorandum Re: Proposed Idea from "RGS", Jan 21, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Drawings and Layouts -- Space Planning Consultant Letter and Background, Apr 29, 1964 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Drinking Water System -- Filtrine Manufacturing Co. -- Proposal, Correspondence, Memoranda, 1963-1967 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Electric System -- Lights, Power, Exhaust, etc. -- Correspondence, Notes, Background, 1963-1966 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Elevators and Conveyors -- Memoranda and Correspondence Re: Proposals, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Equipment Brochures, 1965 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Exterior -- Memoranda, Dec 3, 1964-Oct 5, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Ezra Stoller -- Photographs of Building -- Invoices and List of Photographs, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Fire Protection -- Correspondence, Notes, Permit Amendment Re: Plan Change, Occupancy, Mar 3, 1964-Mar 15, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Floor Design Loadings -- Fact Sheet Memorandum and Floor Plans, Mar 18, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Floor Plans -- Level B through Roof, n.d. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Floor Plans -- New Building, Mar-May 1966 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Floor Plans and Space Assignments, Jul 18, 1966-Feb 1, 1968 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Floors -- Memoranda, Bids and Background Re: Wood and Carpet Floors, 1963-1966 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Floor Spacing and Ceiling Height, Dec 9, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Foundation and Footing -- Memorandum, Feb 16, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - General -- Inter-office Memoranda Re: Building Management, 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - General -- Kitchens, Basement and Office Layout Notes, etc., 1966 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - General -- Memoranda Re: Occupancy Planning, Plate Glass, Fire Hoses, etc., 1963-1966 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - General -- New Building Memoranda -- Miscellaneous -- Security, Budgeting, Kitchens, etc., 1964-1966 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Insurance and Security -- Memoranda, Policy, etc., 1963-1965 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Interior -- Interior Space and Furnishings Planning Memoranda, Dec 311, 1964-Mar 18, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Interior Design Authorization, Sep 29-Oct 21, 1965 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - J. L. Murphy -- Drawings and Sketches, Jul 22-Dec 1, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Janitorial Space -- Memorandum, Jul 29, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Kitchen -- Specifications, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Library -- Shelving Plans, 1963-1967 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Library and Library Operations -- Memoranda Re: Planning Library Services, Oct 31, 1961-Mar 25, 1966 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Maintenance -- Proposals, 1964-1965 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Management -- Cross & Brown -- Proposal, Mar 10, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Management -- Real Estate -- William A. White & Co., Feb 11-Apr 13, 1965 (Box 9, Folder 8)